<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="mecProceedings_schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="mecProceedings_schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="mecProceedings.xsl"?>
<confSubmission xmlns="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei" version="0.05"
  xmlns:ex="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei/Examples"
  xmlns:mei="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei">
  <title>Implementing the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records (FRBR) Model in
    MEI</title>
  <authorList>
    <authorData>
      <authorName>
        <famName>Richts</famName>
        <foreName>Kristina </foreName>
      </authorName>
      <affiliation>n/a</affiliation>
      <email>author1@abc.edu</email>
    </authorData>
    <authorData>
      <authorName>
        <famName>Axel</famName>
        <foreName>Teich Geertinger</foreName>
      </authorName>
      <affiliation>n/a</affiliation>
      <email>author2@abc.edu</email>
    </authorData>
  </authorList>
  <abstract>
    <head>ABSTRACT</head>
    <p>The Music Encoding Initiative’s (MEI) XML schema recommendation not only supports detailed
      encodings of music notation; it also accommodates comprehensive metadata in the file header.
      The attempt to utilize the header for cataloguing projects has proved the need to distinguish
      different levels of description: Some metadata relate to the musical work in general, some
      only to a certain version, or to a specific musical source, for instance. The Functional
      Requirements for Bibliographic Records (FRBR) model, which was developed by the International
      Federation of Library Associations and Institutions (IFLA), was explicitly conceived to
      provide a concept for this distinction within bibliographic records in general. An effort has
      been made within the MEI community to implement the so-called FRBR Group 1 entities (work,
      expression, manifestation, and item) and relationships in the MEI header. The paper gives an
      introduction to the FRBR implementation in MEI and demonstrates how relatively complex source
      situations can be modeled with it. Some limitations and problems are discussed.</p>
  </abstract>
  <div>
    <head>Introduction</head>
    <p>The Music Encoding Initiative (MEI)<annot><ref>http://music-encoding.org</ref>.</annot>
      strives to create a digital, symbolic representation of music notation. One of the advantages
      of the MEI format is that it not only supports detailed encodings of music notation, but also
      the recording of comprehensive metadata in the file header. The attempt to utilize the header
      for cataloguing projects has proved the need to distinguish different levels of description:
      Some metadata relate to the musical work in general, some only to a certain version, or to a
      specific musical source, for instance. At the same time, the increasing internationalization
      in the field of data curation and management leads to higher requirements for libraries and
      research institutions. MEI aims at providing maximum compatibility between the data generated
      by musicological research projects and best-practice cataloguing principles in libraries.</p>
    <p>The Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records (FRBR) model<bibl target="IFLA"/>
      developed by the International Federation of Library Associations and Institutions (IFLA) was
      explicitly conceived to provide a concept for this distinction within bibliographic records in
      general. Against the background of the introduction of the new standard for cataloguing, the
      Resource Description and Access
        (RDA)<annot><ref>http://www.rda-jsc.org/rda.html</ref>.</annot>, which is based on the FRBR
      model as well and will be fully implemented by the Library of Congress and several other
      national libraries in 2013, an effort has been made within the MEI community to implement the
      so-called FRBR Group 1 entities (work, expression, manifestation, and item) and relationships
      in the MEI header. The following presentation gives an introduction to the FRBR implementation
      in MEI and demonstrates how it can be used to model relatively complex source situations.</p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>The MEI Header</head>
    <p>From a music librarian’s perspective, the header of an MEI file offers promising
      opportunities for the coverage and long-term archiving of bibliographic metadata of musical
      sources. At this level, form and content data of sheet music can be enriched with authority
      data. The abundance of data comprises formal elements, such as titles, personal names and
      historical origin to the point of comprehensive instrumentation, water marks or information
      concerning the condition of a source. Depending on the nature of the information, data can be
      encoded in a structured form or as free text.</p>
    <p>The MEI header is based on international cataloguing standards such as International Standard
      Bibliographic Description (ISBD)<bibl target="ISBD"/> or Dublin Core<bibl target="Roland"/>.
      It supports the capture of descriptive, administrative and technical metadata, both for the
      electronic file and the source(s) which were used for the creation of the file. The MEI header
      is divided into five main areas: <list form="ordered">
        <li>Alternative Identifier <term>&lt;altId></term>,</li>
        <li>File Description <term>&lt;fileDesc></term> (including source description),</li>
        <li>Encoding Description <term>&lt;encodingDesc></term>,</li>
        <li>Work Description <term>&lt;workDesc></term> and</li>
        <li>Revision Description <term>&lt;revisionDesc></term>.</li>
      </list></p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>The FRBR Model</head>
    <p>The model of the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records constitutes an abstract
      reference model, which was first published by the International Federation of Library
      Associations and Institutions (IFLA) in 1998. It aims to demonstrate the relations between a
      work and its expressions, relations to responsible persons as well as thematic relations. For
      this purpose, the model defines ten entities within three groups:</p>
    <table>
      <caption>FRBR Entities</caption>
      <tr>
        <td>Group 1 Entities</td>
        <td>Work, Expression, Manifestation, Item</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Group 2 Entities</td>
        <td>Person, Corporate Body</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>Group 3 Entities</td>
        <td>Concept, Object, Event, Place</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    <p>The FRBR model distinguishes four levels of abstraction, or "Group 1" entities: <list>
        <li>Work: FRBR defines a work as a "distinct intellectual or artistic creation", an abstract
          entity because there is no single material object one can point to as the work.</li>
        <li>Expression: An expression is defined as "the intellectual or artistic realization of a
          work in the form of [...] notation, sound, image, object, movement, etc., or any
          combination of such forms". Expressions are also abstract entities.</li>
        <li>Manifestation: A manifestation is defined as "the physical embodiment of an expression
          of a work", including, for instance, manuscripts, books, sound recordings, films, video
          recordings, CD-ROMs, multimedia kits, etc. The manifestation represents all the physical
          objects that bear the same characteristics, with respect to both intellectual content and
          physical form.</li>
        <li>Item: A single exemplar of a manifestation is called an item, e.g., a specific copy of a
          printed score. With manuscripts, item and manifestation levels are nearly identical. A
          manuscript may be regarded as a manifestation having only one item.</li>
      </list></p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Group 1 entities and primary relationships.</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig01.png"/>
    </fig>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Variations/FRBR and Other FRBR-Like Implementations</head>
    <p>In the field of music, several efforts of implementing the FRBR model have been made within
      the last few years. The probably best-known project is the Variations
          Project<annot><ref>http://variations2.indiana.edu/</ref>.</annot> located at Indiana
      University, Bloomington, which for the first time underlined the full benefit of FRBR for use
      in digital libraries. In the context of the Variations2 project a FRBR-like model has been
      developed. This model consists of the five entities "work", "instantiation", "container",
      "media object" and "contributor".</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Variations2 data model.<bibl target="Minibayeva"/></caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig02.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>A comparison of the IFLA’s FRBR model and the model of the Indiana Variations project shows
      some substantial differences, which have to be seen against the practical background of the
      project. Even if the illustration suggests an exact match from container to manifestation and
      from media object to item, FRBR would actually consider the media object a new manifestation
      rather than an item. Furthermore, the FRBR entities "manifestation" and "item" are merged into
      a single entity named "container". Such an approach equates to the common librarian use of
      indexing media by capturing metadata referring to all existing items of a manifestation as
      well as metadata describing only a single item of a manifestation. Existing cataloguing
      formats such as MARC support similar models. The FRBR model strictly distinguishes these two
      entities. Simpler models may be useful for specific projects, but have to be considered
      critically, as the result could be incompatibilities in the long term. In this context, it is
      also important to point out the new Bibframe<annot>Bibliographic Framework Initiative.
          <ref>http://www.loc.gov/bibframe/</ref>.</annot> format proposal of the Library of
      Congress, which intends to replace the data format MARC 21. Bibframe offers an even more
      simplified model, only distinguishing between "creative works" and "instances".</p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>The FRBR Implementation in MEI</head>
    <p>Unlike some other adaptations of FRBR, such as the Indiana Variations project, MEI implements
      the FRBR Group 1 model quite strictly: With the new FRBR module, which is part of the MEI 2013
      schema, MEI offers four elements corresponding to the FRBR entities. The names of these
      elements generally follow those of FRBR: <list>
        <li><term>&lt;work></term> – A container for description at FRBR "work" level.</li>
        <li><term>&lt;expression></term> – For description at FRBR "expression" level.</li>
        <li><term>&lt;source></term> – The MEI equivalent to FRBR "manifestation" level. The name
          "source" is retained mainly for backward compatibility and for its more intuitive
          meaning.</li>
        <li><term>&lt;item></term> – For FRBR "item" level information.</li>
      </list></p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Basic MEI FRBR model</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig03.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>This is the basic structure of the FRBR entity model as implemented in MEI.
        <term>&lt;expression></term> elements are listed in the <term>&lt;expressionList></term>
      element, which is a child of <term>&lt;work></term>. In the same manner,
        <term>&lt;item></term> elements are placed in an <term>&lt;itemList></term> element within
        <term>&lt;source></term>. This structure implies a one-to-many relationship between
        <term>&lt;work></term> and <term>&lt;expression></term>, and between
        <term>&lt;source></term> and <term>&lt;item></term>, respectively, but in agreement with the
      FRBR model not between <term>&lt;expression></term> and <term>&lt;source></term>, which have a
      many-to-many relationship.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Component groups (with <term>@label</term> used instead of <term>&lt;title></term>
        for brevity).</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig04.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Furthermore, each of the four entity-like elements allows a <term>&lt;componentGrp></term>
      element to describe the entity’s constituent parts – for instance, the movements of a work, or
      the individual parts of a set of parts, or the individual folios of a manuscript. Following
      the IFLA’s FRBR recommendation, the child elements are the same type as the parent: the
      constituent parts of a source, for instance, are also described as sources. This construct
      allows the description in full detail at any number of levels. The example shows the principle
      of how to encode a source representing a set of part books, each containing a number of
      pieces. An example at expression level could be the encoding of the structure of an opera: its
      division into acts, acts into scenes, scenes into arias, etc. This technique is also used by
      the MEI metadata editor
          MerMEId<annot><ref>http://www.kb.dk/en/kb/nb/mta/dcm/projekter/mermeid.html</ref>.</annot>
      as demonstrated at this conference’s poster session.</p>
    <p>For the encoding of relations not implied by the structural model itself, MEI provides in
      each of the four entity elements a <term>&lt;relationList></term> element, in which
        <term>&lt;relation></term> child elements may define any relations between entities, like
      the relations between <term>&lt;source></term> and <term>&lt;expression></term> elements, or
      the nature of the relationship between different expressions of the work, or between sources.
      For instance, one source may be defined to be a reprint of another by means of the
      "isReproductionOf" relation.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Relations.</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig05.png"/>
    </fig>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>FRBR vs. Non-FRBR Examples</head>
    <p>In some cases, MEI offers the possibility to encode the same information with or without the
      FRBR module. Please note that we are only discussing the organization of the header here, not
      the encoding of the music. It might be added, though, that the FRBR elements such as
        <term>&lt;source></term> can be linked to their corresponding music encodings by means of
      the "data" attribute. This way, the descriptions of sources (or expressions) in the MEI header
      may be used to describe which portions of the music encoded in an MEI file appear in that
      particular source (or expression).</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Modeling work component structure.</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig06.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Figure 6 shows an example outlining an MEI encoding of a header for Schumann’s
        <title>Lieder-Album für die Jugend</title>. For a detailed description of each of the songs
      (including incipits, for instance) without the FRBR module, each of the songs would be encoded
      as a work in the <term>&lt;workDesc></term> element as shown on the left. This solution
      imposes a certain work concept on the encoding, which may not be the one intended by the
      encoder: It implies that the songs are conceived as individual works encoded in one file. If
      instead the album is conceived as one work containing a number of songs (as – in this case –
      it was definitely intended by the composer), the FRBR module offers a much more suitable
      solution, outlined on the right. The individual songs are now described as component works
      within the main work. This model also allows the encoding of fully detailed metadata at both
      levels: This way the creational history, for instance, can be described both for the main
      work, the album, and for each song individually.</p>
    <p>Figure 7 illustrates the encoding of sources with and without the FRBR module. Shown on the
      left is the outline of a printed source encoded without FRBR. To identify individual copies of
      this source, a number of <term>&lt;physLoc></term> (physical location) elements may be added
      (two in this case).</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Modeling source/item structure</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig07.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>Using this structure, however, there is no way of describing the physical features of the
      individual copies, but only of the entire print run. Also use restrictions at the single copy
      level as shown in the right-most example are impossible to encode in one source element
      without the FRBR module. A workaround would be to describe the copies of the print in two
      distinct <term>&lt;source></term> elements – just like the sibling <term>&lt;work></term>
      elements in the previous example. But then of course the problem would be where to describe
      the features common to all copies of this print. Basically, the <term>&lt;source></term>
      element in non-FRBR MEI is not designed to represent only manifestation or item level but
      both, potentially resulting in ambiguity and inconsistency. In this respect, traditional MEI
      handles sources in a simplified way very much like the Variations and other projects.</p>
    <p>A problem not directly related to the FRBR discussion is that for historical reasons the
        <term>&lt;provenance></term> element is located in the <term>&lt;physDesc></term> element,
      and not in <term>&lt;physLoc></term>, where it logically belongs. Trying to describe the
      provenance of more than one copy of a source within a non-FRBR source description therefore is
      – at best – difficult.</p>
    <p>Using the FRBR module, a clear distinction can be made between the description of the entire
      print run and the individual copies (items). Since items can only have one location, the
        <term>&lt;provenance></term> problem is not equally apparent here, but still it seems to be
      a misconception to regard the provenance of an object part of its physical appearance. The
      drawback of using FRBR for source descriptions is that it complicates the description of
      manuscripts somewhat, because there will be a 1:1 relationship between source and item.
      Therefore it may be difficult to decide what information should be encoded at source level and
      what belongs to the item. From a FRBR point of view, manuscripts are manifestations having
      only one item, which may be helpful to bear in mind when encoding them.</p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Limitations and Problems</head>
    <p>There has been a general concern that the implementation of FRBR in MEI might complicate
      things unnecessarily for some projects. Therefore, the FRBR model is implemented in MEI as an
      optional module, ensuring that those projects which do not need to capture comprehensive
      metadata can use MEI in its traditional structure as far as possible. Especially with
      encodings only including a minimum of metadata, a complex knowledge about the FRBR
      functionality is not required. Nevertheless, the availability of all four FRBR entities
      implies a certain risk to abuse the concepts of FRBR. This challenge can only be addressed by
      a detailed documentation, supplemented by convincing examples, a collection of which is
      currently being compiled as part of the MEI Guidelines. As substantial components of the FRBR
      adaptation are placed in a separate FRBR module the problem has been alleviated to some
      extent. By deactivating this module, merely the two elements <term>&lt;work></term> and
        <term>&lt;source></term> are maintained and can be utilized in a similar way as before. As a
      rule, encodings can be adopted and enriched or diversified in a FRBR-compliant way, if the
      separate FRBR module is activated subsequently.</p>
    <p>Perhaps one of the most intricate aspects in adopting the FRBR model is the interpretation of
      the expression entity. According to FRBR, expressions are different realizations of the work.
      The work as it is notated is one expression; each performance constitutes a new one. This may
      result in a rather complex model with a very large number of expressions and an equally large
      number of relations to clarify their interconnectedness. Furthermore, different versions of
      the notated work – for instance, re-arrangements or revisions – are distinct expressions, and
      one of the questions is where to draw the line between them. What is the amount of variation
      allowed within an expression? The FRBR report states that <quote block="true"><rend
          rend="quotedbl">Strictly speaking, any change in intellectual or artistic content
          constitutes a change in expression. Thus, if a text is revised or modified, the resulting
          expression is considered to be a new expression, no matter how minor the modification may
          be.</rend><bibl target="IFLA"><biblScope from="1:19"/></bibl></quote></p>
    <p>However this is somewhat moderated in the following passage: <quote block="true"><rend
          rend="quotedbl">On a practical level, the degree to which bibliographic distinctions are
          made between variant expressions of a work will depend to some extent on the nature of the
          work itself, and on the anticipated needs of users.</rend><bibl target="IFLA"><biblScope
            unit="page" from="1:19"/></bibl></quote> This does leave some room for the definition of
      an expression’s boundaries.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Restrictive interpretation of the expression entity.</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig08.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>If no variation is allowed at all, each manuscript and each printed edition would require its
      own expression, since there will nearly always be some differences between their contents. The
      result would be a 1:1 relationship between expression and manifestation levels (MEI:
      expression and source), which would make the distinction between the two levels both difficult
      and in effect unnecessary. Only in the case where there are exact reproductions such as
      photocopies or microfilms of the source would there be more than one manifestation to an
      expression, as illustrated in Figure 8.</p>
    <p>Also, with one expression for each source, there is no entity level left for grouping the
      manifestations in, for instance, different versions of the work such as re-instrumentations or
      revisions. Suppose we have two versions of a work: an original version and a revision. A
      number of written or printed sources exist for each of them. Defining each of the sources
      within its own expression (because they differ in some detail) would give us a considerable
      number of sibling expressions. Add to this one expression for each performance. As suggested
      by the FRBR report, relations could be used to define which performance material was used for
      which performance.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Complex expression relations.</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig09.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>The result is a large complex of entities and relations at the expression level (Figure 9).
      It should be noted, however, that this complexity is not due to the way FRBR is implemented in
      MEI; rather, it displays problems inherent to the FRBR model itself. It may be questioned, for
      instance, whether FRBR is right in regarding a performance as an abstract entity.</p>
    <p>To maintain a meaningful and manageable distinction between expression and manifestation
      levels, it might be advisable to only distinguish different versions of the work at the
      expression level, accepting some variation among different sources within that expression. As
      to the encoding of performance data, MEI offers a much simpler alternative, using the
        <term>&lt;history></term> element’s <term>&lt;eventList></term> element to describe
      performances.</p>
    <p>These modifications to the FRBR model are indeed used by the MerMEId metadata editor in order
      to reduce complexity. A justification for this view on performances may be that MEI is
      explicitly notation-centric and thus may regard performances as contextual information rather
      than the primary objects of the encodings. However both approaches are possible and valid in
      MEI and in the end each project will have to choose what is judged to be the most appropriate
      solution.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Using expressions for versions.</caption>
      <graphic target="ex03fig10.png"/>
    </fig>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Conclusion</head>
    <p>By implementing the FRBR module MEI has taken an important step towards a consistent and
      comprehensive bibliographic description of music and musical sources in agreement with
      internationally accepted recommendations. Since – at least for the time being – using the FRBR
      module is optional, projects are still free to choose their way of encoding metadata in MEI.
      It should nevertheless be emphasized, that even if non-FRBR MEI is still valid when activating
      the FRBR module, the concept of the <term>&lt;source></term> element is shifting from being a
      mixed manifestation and item container into being a manifestation level container only. To
      detect how the <term>&lt;source></term> element is to be understood in each case, it may be
      worthwhile considering some indication in the MEI file as to whether the encoding is (or is
      intended to be) FRBR compliant or not. On the other hand, also encoders using all four FRBR
      entity levels may choose to simplify the original FRBR model by encoding, for instance,
      performances as events rather than expressions, so in effect there will be different degrees
      of FRBR compliance. Nevertheless, where strict FRBR Group 1 compliance is required, MEI now
      offers an adequate implementation, ensuring that encoded MEI metadata can be mapped to other
      encoding systems based on the FRBR model.</p>
  </div>
  <biblList>
    <head>WORKS CITED</head>
    <bibl xml:id="IFLA">IFLA Study Group on the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records:
      Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records. Final Report. München: Saur, 1998,
        <ref>http://www.ifla.org/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records</ref>.</bibl>
    <bibl xml:id="Minibayeva">Minibayeva, N. and J. W. Dunn: "A Digital Library Data Model for
      Music," Proceedings of the Second ACM/IEEE-CS Joint Conference on Digital Libraries,
        <ref>http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/544220.544249</ref>, pp. 154–155.</bibl>
    <bibl xml:id="Roland">Roland, P. "Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) DTD and the OCVE", 2nd OCVE
      Meeting. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 2004.</bibl>
    <bibl xml:id="ISBD">Standing Committee of the IFLA Cataloguing Section. ISBD: International
      Standard Bibliographic Description. Consolidated edition. Berlin/München: De Gruyter Saur,
      2011.</bibl>
  </biblList>
</confSubmission>
