<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="mecProceedings_schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="mecProceedings_schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="mecProceedings.xsl"?>
<confSubmission xmlns="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei" version="0.05"
  xmlns:ex="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei/Examples"
  xmlns:mei="http://www.music-encoding.org/ns/mei">
  <title>Encoding, Searching, and Displaying of Music Incipits in the RISM-OPAC</title>
  <authorList>
    <authorData>
      <authorName>
        <famName>Diet</famName>
        <foreName>Jürgen</foreName>
      </authorName>
      <affiliation>N/A</affiliation>
      <email>diet@example.com</email>
    </authorData>
    <authorData>
      <authorName>
        <famName>Gerritsen</famName>
        <foreName>Magda</foreName>
      </authorName>
      <affiliation>N/A</affiliation>
      <email>gerritson@example.com</email>
    </authorData>
  </authorList>
  <abstract>
    <head>ABSTRACT</head>
    <p>The RISM-OPAC (http://opac.rism.info) is a free online catalogue that provides access to the
      data of the RISM series A II (music manuscripts between 1600 and 1800). It has been developed
      by the Bavarian State Library in cooperation with RISM and the State Library of Berlin and was
      launched in June 2010. In March 2011, a new version of the RISM-OPAC has been released that
      includes a searching possibility in the music incipits of the RISM data. Most of the 850.000
      data records (as of September 2013) contain one or several music incipits that describe the
      beginning of instrumental or vocal parts of the music manuscripts using the Plaine&amp;Easie
      code. This paper describes how the music incipits are encoded in Plaine&amp;Easie and how the
      searching for music incipits is done in the RISM-OPAC. Furthermore, the rendering of an
      incipit encoded in Plaine&amp;Easie in a graphical image will be covered. When a RISM-record
      is displayed the user will not see the Plaine&amp;Easie code but the corresponding graphical
      form using the common western music notation. <!-- abstract is too long -->
      <!--Finally, the current developments for the next version of the RISM-OPAC will be explained that include
      among others an improved user interface for searching in the music incipits and the conversion of the data
      records of the RISM series A/II into RDF in order to publish them as linked open data.--></p>
  </abstract>
  <div>
    <head>History and Status Quo of RISM and the RISM-OPAC</head>
    <p>Before describing the RISM-OPAC, a short description of RISM itself will be helpful<annot>All
        URLs in this article have been checked on October 9, 2013.</annot>: <quote><p>"The
          International Inventory of Musical Sources – Répertoire International des Sources
          Musicales (RISM) – is a multinational, non-profit joint venture which aims for
          comprehensive documentation of extant musical sources worldwide. These primary sources are
          manuscripts or printed music, writings on music theory, and libretti. They are housed in
          libraries, archives, monasteries, schools and private collections.</p>
        <p>The organization, founded in Paris in 1952, is the largest and only global operation that
          documents written musical sources. RISM records what exists and where it can be found. As
          a result, musical traditions are protected through cataloguing in a comprehensive
          inventory while also being made available to musicologists and musicians. Such work is
          thus not an end in itself, but leads directly to practical applications."<bibl
            target="rism"/></p></quote> Currently, RISM groups are working in 36 countries and are
      cataloguing their data in a central database hosted by the State Library of Berlin. The RISM
      central office in Frankfurt, Germany, consolidates this data and delivers it monthly to the
      Bavarian State Library where the RISM-OPAC is being developed and hosted (<ref
        target="http://opac.rism.info">http://opac.rism.info</ref>). The first release of the
      RISM-OPAC went online in June 2010; a second release followed in March 2011 and included the
      ability to search by music incipits. The database currently contains around 1,200,000 incipits
      in 850,000 data records and increases by around 25,000 data records each year.</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Homepage of RISM-OPAC at https://opac.rism.info/index.php?id=2&amp;L=1</caption>
      <graphic target="ex02fig01.png"/>
    </fig>
    <p>The most recent new development of the RISM-OPAC is the release of the RISM data records as
      open data in the format MARC-XML. Since July 2013, this data can be downloaded from the
      RISM-OPAC website at <ref target="https://opac.rism.info/index.php?id=8&amp;L=1"
        >https://opac.rism.info/index.php?id=8&amp;L=1</ref>.</p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Encoding of Music Incipits with Plaine&amp;Easie Code</head>
    <div>
      <head>The Plaine&amp;Easie Code</head>
      <p>Plaine&amp;Easie is an alpha-numeric code for encoding musical notation. It is maintained
        by the International Association of Music Libraries (IAML) and by RISM and is described on
        the IAML web pages: <ref
          target="http://www.iaml.info/en/activities/projects/plain_and_easy_code"
          >http://www.iaml.info/en/activities/projects/plain_and_easy_code</ref>. A good overview of
        several musical codes (including Plaine&amp;Easie) can be found in Eleanor Selfridge-Fields’
        book "Beyond Midi"<bibl target="selfridge-field"/>.</p>
      <p>Here is an example for a music incipit and its corresponding notation in
        Plaine&amp;Easie:</p>
      <fig>
        <caption>′4F8-FA″C/4F8.At3GA‴4C/′F8-FB″D/4F</caption>
        <graphic target="ex02fig02.png"/>
      </fig>
    </div>
    <div>
      <head>Cataloguing the RISM incipits</head>
      <p>The RISM country groups are cataloguing their data using the software "Kallisto". Kallisto
        is a proprietary software and distributed to the RISM country groups by the RISM central
        office free of charge. The YouTube channel of the RISM central office contains several
        videos that describe the cataloguing process with Kallisto, among others a video about
        entering incipits in Kallisto: <ref
          target="http://www.youtube.com/user/RISMZentralredaktion"
          >http://www.youtube.com/user/RISMZentralredaktion</ref>. The incipits in the RISM database
        are encoded in Plaine&amp;Easie, and each RISM data record can contain one or more incipits.
        For instrumental music, the first bars of the first violin or the highest instrument are
        used for the incipit. For vocal music, the first bars of the highest voice are used. The
        length of a RISM incipit should be at least 3 bars or 10 non-repeated notes. In its
        typewritten version the code should fit on a single line.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Searching for Music Incipits</head>
    <p>The data of the RISM-OPAC is stored in a FAST-ESP-index (Fast Search &amp; Transfer ASA,
      Enterprise Search Product). FAST is a Norwegian company with focus on data search
      technologies. It has been acquired by Microsoft in 2008.</p>
    <p>There are two index fields that contain the music incipits. The first one includes the
      Plaine&amp;Easie code where the code has been reduced to the pitch values and halftones are
      not considered. The pitch value "B" is represented both as "B" and in its German version "H".
      E.g., the Plaine&amp;Easie code
      <programCode>{"6C'GG"C}{CEED}4D4-/6-{"DDF}{FAA'nB}'4B4-/</programCode> is thus represented in
      the FAST-index as
      <programCode>CGGCCEEDDDDFFAABB|CGGCCEEDDDDFFAAHH|CCCDDDFFF|CCCDDDFFF</programCode></p>
    <p>The RISM-OPAC offers two different search methods by music incipits: with transposition and
      without transposition. For the search with transposition, a second FAST index field is used
      that contains all transposed representations of the original search string. The second FAST
      index field of the above mentioned Plaine&amp;Easie incipit includes this representation: <programCode>
        <![CDATA[CGGCCEEDDDDFFAABB|DAADDFFEEEEGGBBCC|EBBEEGGFFFFAACCDD|
        FCCFFAAGGGGBBDDEE|GDDGGBBAAAACCEEFF|AEEAACCBBBBDDFFGG|
        BFFBBDDCCCCEEGGAA|HFFHHDDCCCCEEGGAA|CGGCCEEDDDDFFAAHH|
        DAADDFFEEEEGGHHCC|EHHEEGGFFFFAACCDD|FCCFFAAGGGGHHDDEE|
        GDDGGHHAAAACCEEFF|AEEAACCHHHHDDFFGG|CCCDDDFFF|DDDEEEGGG|
        EEEFFFAAA|FFFGGGBBB|GGGAAACCC|AAABBBDDD|BBBCCCEEE|
        HHHCCCEEE|FFFGGGHHH|AAAHHHDDD]]>
      </programCode>
    </p>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Displaying the Music Incipits</head>
    <p>For displaying the music incipits, the RISM-OPAC uses a PHP script that invokes a software
      module written in C++ by Dr. Gieseking. The input parameters of this C++-module are the id of
      the incipit and the Plaine&amp;Easie code. The output is an image in the format PNG. If the
      incipit is not a valid Plaine&amp;Easie code, then only the parameter "id" is returned.</p>
    <p>The following URL is an example for invoking the C++-module with the two parameters "id" and
      "incipit":
      http://opac.rism.info/incipit.php?id=20001847&amp;incipit=%25G-2%40c%24bBEA%25B3{%27%276C%27GG%
      27%27C}{CEED}4D4-%2F6-{%27%27DDF}{FAA%27nB}%274B4-%2F</p>
    <p>The result of the C++-module is the following PNG-file:</p>
    <fig>
      <caption>Display results.</caption>
      <graphic target="ex02fig03.png"/>
    </fig>
  </div>
  <div>
    <head>Plans for Further Developments of the RISM-OPAC</head>
    <p>During the year 2013, new developments of the RISM-OPAC are being made that will go online
      probably in spring 2014. These developments are part of the grant for the third project phase
      of the Virtual Library of Musicology. The Virtual Library of Musicology is funded by the
      German Research Foundation in the grant GR 2956/24-2.</p>
    <p>The RISM-OPAC developments in 2013 include <list form="marked">
        <li>the introduction of institutional and collection level views to the RISM data so that
          other institutions can integrate a subset of the RISM data into their websites</li>
        <li>improvements in the display of search results (e.g., for persons)</li>
        <li>enabling the search for RISM data records with digitizations</li>
        <li>an improved incipit search that recognizes half tones and has a virtual keyboard as user
          interface for entering the search melody</li>
        <li>the integration of the RISM series B/I (collective music prints) in the RISM-OPAC</li>
        <li>the publication of the RISM data in RDF (i.e., as linked open data) and</li>
        <li>bug fixes.</li>
      </list></p>
    <p>In the medium term, more developments of the RISM-OAPC are planned but are dependent on
      appropriate funding. These plans include <list form="marked">
        <li>the integration of the RISM series A/I (individual music prints) in the RISM-OPAC</li>
        <li>improved integration of authority files (GND and VIAF) and</li>
        <li>implementing new requirements of the successor software of Kallisto.</li>
      </list></p>
  </div>
  <biblList>
    <head>WORKS CITED</head>
    <bibl xml:id="rism">RISM web site. <ref target="http://www.rism.info/en/organisation.html"
        >http://www.rism.info/en/organisation.html</ref></bibl>
    <bibl xml:id="selfridge-field">Selfridge-Field, Eleanor. Beyond MIDI: The handbook of musical
      codes. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1997.</bibl>
  </biblList>
</confSubmission>
